<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reply to the Danish papers presented to the members of Parliament the 23 of February last, concerning the question: whether England should not assist the Swede, as well as the Dutch do the Dane. Answered by a true English man.</title>
            <author>True English man.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91665</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1071</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E972_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207744</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866780</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866780</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119066</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91665)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119066)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 144:E972[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reply to the Danish papers presented to the members of Parliament the 23 of February last, concerning the question: whether England should not assist the Swede, as well as the Dutch do the Dane. Answered by a true English man.</title>
                  <author>True English man.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "march 2d. 1658.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Sweden --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="reply">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119066:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A REPLY To the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Papers preſented to the members of Parliament the 23 of <hi>February</hi> laſt, Concerning the Queſtion: <hi>Whether</hi> England <hi>ſhould not aſſiſt the</hi> Swede, <hi>as well as the</hi> Dutch <hi>do the</hi> Dane. Anſwered by a true Engliſh man.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou have deſired to know, what the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Party can anſwer for themſelves and their King concerning the Papers which were offered to the Members of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in favour of the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> to diſſwade <hi>England</hi> from inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medling in the quarrel which is between the <hi>Swede</hi> and him; to the end that both ſides being heard, and the Circumſtances of the Controverſie being opened in a ſober way and without paſſion and partiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119066:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>power of thoſe that oppoſe you, is to make your ſelves ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and to give the Cauſe loſt. To conclude then, it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that <hi>England</hi> muſt now either renounce wholly all Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Proteſtant Cauſe, and give it up into the hands of the Enemy, or elſe appear, and that ſuddenly in this inſtant, in this way to uphold it.</p>
            <p>As for the Plea which the Papers make for <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> it is grounded upon four main Arguments, to which all particulars may be referred.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Becauſe (as they ſay) the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> is the unjuſt Invader and Oppreſſour of the <hi>Dane.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Secondly, Becauſe the States of <hi>Holland</hi> by their Intereſt in Trading in the <hi>Balthick</hi> Sea, and by their ſpecial League with the <hi>Dane,</hi> are bound to aſſiſt him.</item>
               <item>3. Thirdly, Becauſe <hi>England</hi> is obliged by the Peace made with the <hi>Dane</hi> not to ſee him wronged.</item>
               <item>4. Fourthly, Becauſe the States of <hi>Holland</hi> have communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated unto this State their deſign of ſuccouring <hi>Denmark,</hi> and not being diſſwaded from it, they did take ſilence for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Concerning the firſt; namely that the <hi>Swede</hi> hath invaded the <hi>Dane,</hi> is only ſaid, but not proved; whereas the contrary is a moſt evident truth, as can be undeniably proved, namely that the <hi>Dane</hi> and the <hi>Dutch</hi> have, without any cauſe given to them by the <hi>Swede,</hi> moſt injuſtly invaded him, ſo that he is a meer De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant of himſelf againſt them. For it is known to all the world, that when the <hi>Swede</hi> was engaged in the War with <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and alſo in League with <hi>Denmark</hi> and the <hi>Dutch,</hi> that the <hi>Dutch</hi> made a League with the <hi>Dantzikers</hi> to oppoſe him; that they and the <hi>Dane</hi> together brought a Fleet of Ships of War into the <hi>Balthick</hi> ſea (the <hi>Dutch</hi> of forty and odd, the <hi>Dane</hi> of nine or ten ſails, to ſhew his dependence upon them) to overpower him: and that the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſent ſoldiers unto <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> to fight againſt him, that he might not ſettle in the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that which he had taken from his enemy; and when this was not enough to hinder him, both the <hi>Dutch</hi> and the <hi>Dane</hi> dealt with the <hi>Muſcovite</hi> to aſſault him in <hi>Liefland,</hi> promiſing to ſtop all ſuccour from <hi>Riga</hi> by ſea, whiles he did beſiege it by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119066:2"/>land; and when this would not yet ſufficiently divert him, the <hi>Dane</hi> by the <hi>Hollanders</hi> inſtigation, (contrary to all Leagues formerly ſworn and ratified between them, and notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all inſtances made by the <hi>Swede</hi> to treat, and offers to give all due ſatisfaction to the <hi>Dane,</hi> if any injury was done ſince the former League concluded) I ſay the <hi>Dane</hi> raiſed three po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Armies, and invaded the <hi>Swede</hi> in <hi>Bremen,</hi> and in <hi>Sweden</hi> it ſelf both where it joins to <hi>Sconen,</hi> and where it borders upon <hi>Norway:</hi> and all this was done before the <hi>Swede</hi> ſhewed the leaſt Hoſtility againſt <hi>Denmark</hi> or the <hi>Dutch,</hi> nay whiles the <hi>Dutch</hi> were treating to renew or confirm their former Leagues with him at <hi>Elbing;</hi> nay, after they had obtained all their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and had promiſed to ratifie the Treaty: ſo that the breach having been made by the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Dane</hi> ſo many ways with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any cauſe given by him, and after all ſatisfaction offered by Treaties, as is known to all that know any thing of theſe Tranſactions, it muſt be thought to be a wonderfull impudence to call the <hi>Swede</hi> the Invader of <hi>Denmark,</hi> or to aſſert that he gave cauſe to the preſent breach which is between the Northern Kingdoms; for it had been madneſs in him to have given any cauſe of breaking with the <hi>Dane,</hi> when both the <hi>Pole</hi> and the <hi>Muſcovite</hi> were joyned againſt him. But the truth is, that at the perſwaſion of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and upon their engagement to him to maintain with him the War againſt <hi>Sweden,</hi> the <hi>Dane</hi> broke the peace with <hi>Sweden,</hi> which the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Agent in the <hi>Hague</hi> hath publikely declared to their face, when they lingred to ſend his Maſter ſuccour: the deſign then of the <hi>Dane</hi> was to take his time when the <hi>Swede</hi> was beſet round with enemies in <hi>Poland,</hi> to invade him in his own Country, that he might be ruined at one inſtant, both at home and abroad; hoping by that means that the three Northern Crowns (as then the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> was heard to ſay) might again come upon one head, meaning his own; and indeed, in humane appearance it might have been ſo, if God had not wonderfully carried him along out of <hi>Poland,</hi> and brought him over the ſea to march with an Army toward <hi>Coppenhagen</hi> to be revenged of the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery which was uſed againſt him. Theſe Truths are ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable, that no man can have a face to deny them; for this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119066:3"/>cauſe the Papers paſs by the firſt occaſion of the War, and would faſten the crime of an innvaſion upon the <hi>Swede</hi> only ſince the Treaty concluded at <hi>Roskild,</hi> as if the <hi>Swede</hi> had without cauſe broken the Peace concluded there in <hi>February,</hi> 1657. But when the cauſe ſhall be weighed, as then it was, and as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it fell out to be by the malice of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and falſhood of the <hi>Daniſh,</hi> then it may be determined impartially, whether the <hi>Swede</hi> or the <hi>Dane</hi> did give cauſe to the continuance of the War. The caſe at that Treaty was a juſt defence of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf on the <hi>Swediſh</hi> part, and a juſt Revenge againſt the <hi>Daniſh</hi> invaſion, who had deſerved to be dealt withal as he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to have dealt with the <hi>Swede,</hi> that is, to be deprived of all his Dominions, as he had deſigned to deprive the <hi>Swede</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by his invaſion; yet the <hi>Swede</hi> was ſo merciful to him, that when he had all in his power, he reſtored unto him more then be deſerved: for contenting himſelf with ſuch Territories as were a part of his ſecurity, he remitted unto him the mony, the Soldiers and the Ships, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> chief things, which by the conditions of Peace he was bound to furniſh him withall, and ſo put him in a condition to live ſtill as a King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> upon condition that he would be faithfull to the League made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them in time to come, which was not to be leagued with his enemies any more, nor to contrive any further diſturbance to his affairs, when he ſhould be retired from him to march back again into <hi>Poland;</hi> But his back was no ſooner turned, when he was in a poſture to march into <hi>Poland,</hi> but the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy of his enemies, the <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> and the <hi>Auſtrian,</hi> with whom the <hi>Dane</hi> was alſo ſecretly comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, was diſcovered; for it was manifeſt that the <hi>Dutch</hi> had not gained their ends, neither at the Treaty of <hi>Elbing,</hi> nor at the Treaty of <hi>Roſchild;</hi> this made them put to all their ſtrength and Induſtry to bring over the <hi>Brandenburger</hi> to their Party, and to put the <hi>Dane</hi> upon a reſolution with their help to regain what he had loſt, to whom the <hi>Poliſh</hi> and <hi>Auſtrian</hi> aſſiſtance being joyned, they lay the plot to compaſs their firſt ends at an after game. Of this deſign the <hi>Swede</hi> had undoubted diſcoveries, not only by the <hi>Daniſh</hi> not ſurrendring of the places neceſſary for his ſecurity in due time, according to conditions, but by the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119066:3"/>Tranſactions which he found agreed upon amongſt theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federetes, to work his ruine by beſetting him on all ſides before and behind; for which cauſe he was neceſſitated to prevent the unavoidable danger wherewith he was threatned, by ſhutting the back-door, and providing for his own ſafety; ſo that the effect of the Treaty of <hi>Roſchild</hi> not being performed, but vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by the <hi>Dane,</hi> there was no new invaſion made by the <hi>Swede</hi> upon the <hi>Dane,</hi> but the former defenſive War was continued, <hi>Nam durat bellum, dum belli cauſa durat; nec pro Aggreſſore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendus eſt, qui primus ferit, ſed qui cauſam dat feriendi;</hi> which is manifeſt by the immediate effect of their Confederacy; for the <hi>Swede</hi> no ſooner went back again to make ſure the paſſage of the Sound for his own ſafety, but all theſe Confederates were inſtantly in Arms againſt him; by which it was apparent, that their deſigns had been formed before hand: So that if there had been no more in the Caſe but that the <hi>Dutch</hi> having made the Treaty of <hi>Elbing</hi> void by their own default of Ratification, and being juſtly excluded from the mediation at the Treaty of <hi>Roſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child,</hi> and the <hi>Dane</hi> being ſtill in League with them who were his chief enemies, and who had more power to do him miſchief through the Sound then the <hi>Dane</hi> himſelf there was an abſolute neceſſity that the <hi>Swede</hi> ſhould ſecure himſelf from the invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which was prepared againſt him; by all which it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that both firſt and laſt the <hi>Swede</hi> is the Defendant and oppreſſed, and not the Aggreſſor; and that the <hi>Dutch</hi> are the Original cauſe, and the Fomenters of all this War, and all to maintain their pretended Intereſt of Trade into the <hi>Balthick</hi> ſea by force, when they might have done it by amiable agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, both for themſelves and their friends the <hi>Dantzikers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the ſecond Argument, which is taken from the Intereſt of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> that their Trade in the <hi>Balthick</hi> ſea ſhould be maintained in Peace, Wars being prejudicial thereunto; and that the reſpective Northern Kings ſhould be maintained in their Kingdoms and Territories; to which effect they ſay, That they did firſt contract with <hi>Sweden</hi> a defenſive League and Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in the year 1640, and afterward to the ſame end made another Defenſive League with the King and Kingdom of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> with the approbation of <hi>Sweden</hi> in the year 1649. by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119066:4"/>which they are obliged to aſſiſt him, and in conformity to that Obligation have ſent their Fleet to relieve him, as they ſay.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is to be granted, that their Trade in the <hi>Balthick</hi> Sea is one of their great concernments, and that Wars ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily are prejudicial to Trade, is alſo a Truth: but if ſo, then their conſcience ought to be ſearched and tried upon theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatories.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Why they did ſtir up War in the <hi>Balthick</hi> Sea?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Why they did ſtir up the <hi>Dane</hi> to break his Covenants with the <hi>Swede,</hi> after that they brought a ſtrong Fleet of men of War into the Sea?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Why they did not ſecure their Trade by amiable Treaties with the <hi>Swede,</hi> as well now, as formerly they did with the King <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Why they did make themſelves his Enemy in the <hi>Poliſh</hi> War? had it not been better for all Proteſtants to have had a Proteſtant Prince there then a Jeſuited Papiſt?</p>
            <p>Therefore the Allegation and Plea for Peace being ſo directly contrary to their manifeſt practice, ſheweth that either this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is a Politick Deceit, under the colour whereof they ſeek ſomething elſe, or elſe they think all men fools, and not able to diſcern the Language of their actions, which ſpeak clearly ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, namely, that having ſet their Northern Kings one againſt another, they would weaken them ſo that both ſhould fall under their power, whereupon they would be able to command the Trade at their own pleaſure: for when the <hi>Dane</hi> ſhould not be able to ſubſiſt without them, and the <hi>Swede</hi> ſhould be ruined by them, then they ſhould do what they would in the Trade; And all Intelligent men can ſee that their actions all along ſpeak nothing elſe but this. It is true, that their great concernment is Trade in the <hi>Balthick</hi> Sea: and it is alſo true, that Wars are ordinarily prejudicial to Trade, namely when they cannot mannage the War to their own advantage; but if by War they can hinder all others from Trading beſides them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or that none can Trade without their leave, (as now in the <hi>Indies</hi> they have begun to do) then War is ſo far from being prejudicial to Trade, that it becomes the only advantage thereof; and that their preſumption is ſuch that they mean,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119066:4"/>to carry it this way is clear, not only by all their proceedings hitherto, and by their care that <hi>England</hi> ſhould not intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle (which is only able to break this Deſign) but by their Reſolution expreſſed in oppoſition to <hi>Englands</hi> intermeddling, by theſe words uſed in their Conſultation concerning <hi>England, Aut caedas aut cedas,</hi> either beat or give way. By all which it appears, as alſo by the Letter which their Ambaſſadour <hi>Van Beuning</hi> wrote to his Maſters the States, that the name of Peace is indeed in their mouth, but nothing but War in their heart, Counſels and Actions; and which above all this is yet ſo much the more evident, becauſe that ſince the time that the publike Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> have at the <hi>Hague</hi> diſſwaded the States from promoting the War in the <hi>Sound,</hi> declaring in the name of their Maſters that it would be taken as promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it againſt themſelves, they have made greater preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for War then ever, by leavying an extraordinary Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution to maintain it; and preparing a greater Fleet then any heretofore to employ in it: and yet they would have the world ſo blind and fooliſh, as to believe that no ſuch thing is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.</p>
            <p>As concerning their Leagues with <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Sweden</hi> (for they alledge 1649. before 1640) they proſtitute their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit very ſhamefully in that buſineſs; becauſe they mention on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their Obligation to <hi>Denmark,</hi> whereas their League with <hi>Sweden</hi> is more ancient then that with <hi>Denmark;</hi> and then it was a double League; one in 1640. and another in 1645. and both very ſtrict and ſpecial for mutual Defence, whereas the League with <hi>Denmark</hi> was but in general terms, and made with conſent of <hi>Sweden,</hi> ſo that in it nothing is concluded to the prejudice of <hi>Sweden;</hi> but in their League with <hi>Sweden</hi> there is particular mention made of the <hi>Dane</hi> by name, as being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of that he had many wayes tranſgreſſed <hi>Contra Jus Gentium, Pacta, Conventa, &amp; morem ab antiquo obſervatum,</hi> which they never yet could ſay of the Swedes; but chiefly it is obſervable that in the fore-named League whereas on the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh ſide <hi>France</hi> and the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> and on the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſide, <hi>France, England</hi> and <hi>Venice</hi> are comprehended as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, <hi>Denmark</hi> is left out by both parties, which in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119066:5"/>League between them and <hi>Denmark</hi> cannot be in reference to <hi>Sweden,</hi> ſeeing it was made with the conſent of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Sweden:</hi> not did that League reſpect only the occaſion of the War then compoſed between the two Crowns, whereof mention is made in the firſt and ſecond Articles, but it relates to future times, as in the third Article appears: <hi>Si poſt modium alia quacun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> de cauſa &amp; praetextu Sm.</hi> 
               <hi>Rm.</hi> 
               <hi>Mtem.</hi> 
               <hi>&amp; Regnum</hi> Sweſiae <hi>&amp; Ei ſubjectas Provincias &amp; ſubditos bello adoriatur,</hi> which in the ſixth Article is thus enlarged, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t neuter alterutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us hoſtem</hi> (nempe imprimis Danum contra quem Foedus inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debatur) <hi>qui nunc eſt in praeſens hoſtis, aut deinceps exiſtere po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit, conſilio, ope, pecunia, commeatu, milite, Navibus, nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, armis, pulvere pyrio aut munitionibus ulliſve rebus bellicis adjuvet;</hi> and all this was confirmed by an expreſs Treaty of Warantie or Security for 49 years from that time forward, with theſe plain words: <hi>Si quid à Rege</hi> Daniae <hi>ejusve ſucceſſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aut Miniſtris in alterutrius Partis Subditorum prejudicium ac detrimentum actum, &amp; Pactis contraventum fuerit, nec amice ademonitus Rex</hi> Daniae <hi>emendaverit, Pactis<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſatisfecerit, ex prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripto initi Foederis hujusq promiſſi opem laturi ſunt.</hi> So that the <hi>Dutch</hi> are guilty of a threefold breach of Covenant againſt the <hi>Swedes.</hi> 1. That they did not aſſiſt the <hi>Swede</hi> when the <hi>Dane</hi> did ſo treacherouſly invade him, as hath been ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. 2. That they themſelves did ſtir up the <hi>Dane</hi> to invade <hi>Sweden,</hi> as alſo hath been made to appear. 3. That they have aſſiſted <hi>Denmark</hi> againſt <hi>Sweden,</hi> when according to their own and all mens Confeſſion the <hi>Dane</hi> was the Aggreſſor and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vader of <hi>Sweden;</hi> for when the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> was the firſt time in <hi>Holſtein,</hi> before ever he came into <hi>Zealand,</hi> they did ſend to the <hi>Dane</hi> money, Souldiers, Ships, and all other things, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they could ſend, and he deſired of them.</p>
            <p>And whereas in this place, they make mention of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Elbing</hi> to blame the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> that he did wave it upon a pretence that ſome preliminar Declarations were firſt to be made, and aſſurances given; and in the mean time on the ninth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1658. he went unto the Iſland of <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> this is like all the reſt; for it is to be noted that the Treaty of <hi>Elbing</hi> was concluded between the. <hi>Swede</hi> and the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119066:5"/>
               <hi>Dutch</hi> Ambaſſadors on the firſt of <hi>September,</hi> 1656. then the Ratification, was promiſed to be made by the Stater within ſome few months; but they performed not their promiſe but protracted the time till the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> went into <hi>Zealand</hi> which was two whole years, wanting three weeks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> is, till the ninth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 58. Then when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Miracle was become Maſter of <hi>Zealand,</hi> they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of their own accord, when as before that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Swede</hi> had urged them almoſt a hundred times to ſend it with much entreaty; whereupon when it came being too late, it was juſtly refuſed to be accepted till ſome preliminary De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations ſhould be made, and aſſurances given to prevent future juglings, which formerly they had uſed on their part; and yet this is now alledged as a great wrong done to them that the League was not confirmed, when they themſelves were the only cauſe of it by delaying the Ratification, that they might deal underhand with the <hi>Moſcovite</hi> and with <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> to betray the <hi>Swede,</hi> whiles they pretended to treat with him: which Treaty was indeed altogether (if they had been honeſt) needleſs, becauſe there were two Leagues in full force between them at that time: but they propoſing a confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe Leagues, the King would not refuſe it, but was extream willing to have it done, ſeeing it would have ſecured him againſt the <hi>Dane;</hi> but their Deſign was only to propoſe it to make him more ſecure, and the better to colour their perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious dealing in ſtirring up enemies againſt him; ſo that it is to be wondered they ſhould have the impudence now to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for their juſtification a thing ſo notoriouſly ſhameful and known to all the World to have been a colour of their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery.</p>
            <p>The third Argument alledged concerning the League be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> is all of a piece with the former. For the <hi>Dane</hi> ſent Ambaſſadors into <hi>England</hi> to Treat for a League before the War broke forth between the Parliament and <hi>Holland:</hi> this he did not ſo much for himſelf, ss to ſerve the turn of the <hi>Dutch;</hi> that is to help them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Parliament; for when the Treaty was even upon concluding, the <hi>Dane</hi> arreſted without any colour or pretence
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119066:6"/>of Juſtice, the Engliſh Fleet in the <hi>Sound</hi> to gratifie the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> who were reſolved to break with <hi>England.</hi> So under the pretence of a Treaty he favoured the <hi>Dutch</hi> deſigns of weakening <hi>England</hi> by ſea. Then when the War was at an end, the <hi>Dutch</hi> who promiſed to ſave him harmleſs, made conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for him with <hi>England,</hi> and made reſtitution of damages for the ſhips and goods arreſted. Thus the <hi>Dane</hi> was nothing in all <hi>his</hi> applications to <hi>England</hi> but the Vaſſal of the <hi>Dutch</hi> to do their work: and now in the War with <hi>Sweden</hi> he muſt be their drudge to bear the burden of their Intereſt; therefore the Leagues made with him are broken by him, or kept at their pleaſure. Now if he and they have had no conſcience to break all their Leagues with <hi>Sweden,</hi> who is the Confederate of <hi>England,</hi> without any communication of Counſel with this State, or without any endeavour to have matters of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rerce (if any were) compoſed, nay againſt all fair offers of ſatisfact on, in caſe of wrong done; I ſay, if the <hi>Dane</hi> hath thus behaved himſelf in the obſerving of that League, in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as if it had not been, I ſee not any Obligation lying upon <hi>England</hi> to favour him for it; for <hi>England</hi> had no reſpect unto him but for the <hi>Dutch</hi>-ſake, nor did he ever reſpect <hi>England</hi> but upon their account at that time: Whereas in all former occaſions he hath ſhewed himſelf rather an Enemy then a Friend to this State; and in this occaſion he hath made himſelf the Chief Enemy to the Proteſtant Cauſe, which is the great &amp; main Intereſt of <hi>England</hi> to have it ſupported; for this is the great Wheel upon which all the Leagues which <hi>England</hi> hath with Forraigners, and chiefly with Proteſtants, do turn and are ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; ſo that if any State doth overthrow that Intereſt, which <hi>Denmark</hi> in this Caſe hath endeavoured to do, the Obligation which <hi>England</hi> hath unto it, muſt ceaſe, becauſe the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it is made void; therefore the <hi>Dane</hi> at this time having done this, <hi>England</hi> ſhould be ſo far from aſſiſting him, that it ought rather to help him to receive his juſt reward, which is, that he ſhould ſuffer that which he hath endeavoured to bring upon his harmleſs Neighbour.</p>
            <p>The laſt Argument is, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> having communicated their deſign to aſſiſt <hi>Denmark</hi> with <hi>England,</hi> they were not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119066:6"/>from it; but it ſilently was aſſented unto; whereupon the Admiral <hi>Opdam</hi> was ſent thither, and did not of ſet purpoſe, but occaſionally come to fight with the <hi>Swedes;</hi> ſeeing the States intention was to work out a peaceable agreement, whereunto the concurrence of <hi>England</hi> was deſired. Now to ſhew that there is no more truth in this then in all the fore going Allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: let us examine firſt that which doth concern <hi>Opdam</hi> by the action it ſelf, and his behaviour in performing of it. Firſt, the preparation of ſo many fire-ſhips which <hi>Opdam</hi> brought along with him, ſhews that a fight was purpoſely intended to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Swediſh Fleet; And the Inſtructions which he had from the States his Maſters, whereof a Copy was found in the Vice-Admirals <hi>Witte Wittſon</hi> his Cabinet, * <hi>Sub Lit. A.</hi> whoſe ſhip was taken by the <hi>Swedes,</hi> do ſhew that he was charged in expreſs terms to deſtroy the Swediſh Fleet in whole or in part, wherever he ſhould meet with it; Nor is there any one word of any peaceable tranſaction mentioned therein: And indeed <hi>Opdam</hi> his behaviour in paſſing through the <hi>Sound</hi> was anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thereunto; for when the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> had ſent a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage unto him, before he did enter into the <hi>Sound</hi> to know the purpoſe of his coming thither, he returned him no anſwer, but ſent the Letter and Meſſage which came from him with a Galiot to his Maſters, and in the mean time came on towards the <hi>Sound,</hi> and when he came within it, his behaviour was altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hoſtile; for having caſt Anchor directly over againſt the Caſtle of <hi>Chronenburg,</hi> and being ſaluted by it in a friendly manner, he returned to it no friendly re-ſalutation, but the wind ſerving him favourably, he fell directly upon the Swediſh Fleet with whole broad-ſides to overthrow it, which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly they ſo anſwered, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> have had no cauſe to boaſt of a Victory, although in <hi>Holland</hi> they made the people believe ſo. And this will ſuffice to ſhew the falſhood of that which is alledged, concerning the purpoſe of their Fleet in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Sound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As concerning their Intention of Peace, wherein they ſhould have deſired <hi>England</hi> to concur with them, that is no more true then the reft; for at the ſame time when this Intention was held forth unto <hi>England,</hi> it is known that in <hi>Holland</hi> a Fleet
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119066:7"/>was preparing of 200. Sails, not to bring the <hi>Anſtrian, Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgiſh</hi> and <hi>Poliſh</hi> Forces into <hi>Zealand</hi> and <hi>Tunen</hi> only, but even into <hi>Schonen,</hi> and over the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Frontiers, whereupon Letters were ſent unto the <hi>Dane</hi> to diſſwade him from all Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Peace with the <hi>Swede,</hi> promiſing him that they would employ their whole might in the quarrel; and to this effect the two hundreth penny was yielded unto, for which a long time had been endeavoured, which without a great and urgent concernment would never have been granted, and which doth amount to many Millions; and the deſign of theſe prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations was openly given out in <hi>Holland</hi> to bring <hi>England</hi> under the Command of <hi>Holland</hi> at ſea, to receive the Law from them, and to cut off the Correſpondency which might be between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Sweden;</hi> whereupon the words formerly mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Aut Caedas aut Cedas,</hi> were made uſe of to declare their deſign towards <hi>England:</hi> And were not theſe peaceable inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? Were they not amiable Purpoſes with which <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> ſhould concur, and at which it ſhould ſit ſtill and be ſilent?</p>
            <p>But that at the communication of their deſign of ſending a Fleet into the Sound to aſſiſt the <hi>Dane,</hi> there was no ſuch ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Aſſent given by <hi>England,</hi> as they pretend, is manifeſt by that which is publiquely known, concerning the Remonſtrance which the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador and Engliſh Reſident made jointly unto the States about this very buſineſs, declaring unto them, that if they did proceed in a hoſtile way to oppoſe the <hi>Swede,</hi> that it would be taken by their Maſters as done unto themſelves, would and accordingly reſent it. It is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to the world what the Heroick deſigns and intentions of the late Lord Protector of bleſſed memory were, what eſteem he had of the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and how well he wiſhed him ſucceſs, and intended the Wel-fare of the Evangelical Cauſe in all his Enterpriſes; therefore it will be underſtood by all that knew him, that he never would be ſilent, or ſeem to give any aſſent unto ſuch a Communication: therefore this Allegation is a manifeſt Calumny againſt his upright meanings; and the contrary is moſt evidently true, that he hath both pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely and privately, both here and in <hi>Holland</hi> made it known
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119066:7"/>and declared, that if they did not alter their Purpoſe, he would alſo put himſelf in a poſture to croſs them therein; and if his untimely ſickneſs and death had not prevented the effect of his Reſolutions, perhaps the <hi>Dutch</hi> before this time would have ſeen it; but ſince his death, his Highneſs who now is treading in the glorious ſteps of his renowned Father, hath ſhewed by the effects that <hi>England</hi> doth not intend to connive and to be ſilent at ſuch a threacherous deſign, whereby for covetous ends the Proteſtant-Intereſt in <hi>Europe</hi> will not only be undermined, bat directly overthrown, if the <hi>Swede</hi> be ruined in favour of thoſe who for ſelf-ends make no conſcience of breaking Leagues, and concur even to betray the common Cauſe into the hands of the profeſſed enemies thereof, with whom they confederate themſelves to fight againſt it; and how far the <hi>Dutch</hi> have joined themſelves with <hi>Spain</hi> to this effect againſt the Intereſt of their antient friends, and concur with the houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> to ſtrengthen him againſt the Proteſtant Party, God to whom theſe Papers in the Cloſe have made an Appeal, doth ſee and will judge: and as hitherto he hath not altogether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nived at their Jugling with their friends in their Treaties, but hath turned all their craftineſs and plots into folly, and taken them in their own devices; <hi>(for he knoweth the ſecrets of hearts)</hi> ſo it will be their wiſdom henceforth to learn plainer dealing, and not to lift their horn on high, nor to ſpeak with a ſtiff neck, as their cuſtom is, and hath been: which I ſhall beſeech the Lord in Mercy to grant unto them for their own good, that yet they may partake of the Bleſſings which the God of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs hath in ſtore for thoſe that walk uprightly and humbly in his preſence; and this ſhall be all the evil that I ſhall wiſh them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119066:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Lit. A.</hi> The Copy of the Order to the <hi>States</hi> Admiral <hi>Opdam</hi> intercepted.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have acquainted their High and Mighty Lordſhips with the <hi>Clauſule</hi> your Lordſhip mentioned in your Letter of the ſecond Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, wherein your Lordſhip referreth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, whether you ought not to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that in caſe <hi>Coppenhagen</hi> ſhould be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred, you ſhould notwithſtanding fall upon the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Fleet wherever you could find them, and if poſſible, ruine ſame? Whereupon their High and Mighty Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips have thought good to command me to give you notice, (which by Vertue of their Order theſe preſents do give you) that it is the intention of their High and Mighty Lordſhips, that the Tenor of the ſixth Article of your Inſtruction ſhould be executed without any reſpect; not only if <hi>Coppenhaguen</hi> ſhould yet hold out, but likewiſe if the ſame ſhould be taken, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as your Lordſhip ſhall plainly ſee out of the Orders of the States General, which ere long ſhall be ſent to your Lordſhips hands. In the mean while your Lordſhip may aſſure your ſelt by theſe preſents in the name of their High and Mighty Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, that in caſe <hi>Coppenhaguen</hi> ſhould be loſt, and any op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity preſent it ſelf to be Maſter, or ſpoil and ruine the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Fleet, your Lordſhig laying hold on ſuch an occaſion ſhould do well, and by ſo acting, deſerve Commendation and Honor; and contrarywiſe, if any ſuch opportunity ſhould be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected, your Lordſhip ſhould expect nothing but diſgrace and blame; To which purpoſe theſe preſents are only intended, the which I now conclude.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Hague,</hi>
                  <date>the 19. of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1658.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>This Letttr was read and approved of by their High and Mighty Lordſhips in a full Aſſembly. JOHAN <hi>de</hi> WITTE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
